Finding Aid for Vice President for Student Affairs (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library
- Henry Johnson, Vice-President of Student Services, 1950-1985; 1972-1985
  - Annual Files, 1972-1985
    - 1981-1982 Annual File (fragment), 1976-1982 1981-1982
      - Dannemiller, Kathleen (Assistant to Johnson), 1981 (Box 16)
      - Executive Officers (Johnson's Notes), 1981-1982 (Box 16)
      - Functional Review (of Office of Student Services), 1981 (Box 16)
      - Health Service, 1981-1982 (Box 16)
      - Housing, 1981-1982 (Box 16)
      - Major Events Office, 1976-1982 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Student Assembly, 1981-1982 (Box 16)
      - Personnel, 1980-1982 (Box 16)
      - Regents-Executive Officers Retreat, 1978-1981
        - Budget and Economics, 1981 (Box 16)
        - Intellectual Assets, 1979-1981 (Box 16)
        - Planning, 1981 (Box 16)
        - Students, 1978-1981 (Box 16)
    - 1982-1983 Annual file (fragment), 1980-1983 1982-1983
      - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, 1981-1983 (Box 16)
      - Functional Review (of Office of Student Services), 1982-1983 (Box 16)
      - Housing, 1981-1983 (Box 16)
      - Major Events Office, 1976-1982 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Student Assembly, 1980-1982 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Union, 1981-1983 (Box 16)
      - Regents, 1979-1983 (Box 16)
    - 1983-1984 Annual file, 1971-1984 1983-1984
      - Black Student Retention, 1981-1983 (Box 17)
      - Career Planning and Placement, 1981-1983 (Box 17)
      - Community Services, 1979-1984 (Box 17)
      - Correspondence and Memos, 1980-1984 (Box 17)
      - Disabled Student Services, 1973-1983 (Box 17)
      - Family Memo, 1982-1984 (Box 17)
      - Housing Bulletin, 1982-1984 (Box 17)
      - Housing Reports, 1975-1983 (Box 17)
      - Minority Concerns, 1979-1982 (Box 17)
      - Minority Enrollment, 1981-1983 (Box 17)
      - Minority Student Services, 1980-1982 (Box 17)
      - Minority Task Force, 1971-1981 (Box 17)
      - Office of Vice-President Student Services Internal file, 1980-1983 (Box 17)
      - Student Code, 1979-1984 (Box 17)
      - Student Fees and Aid, 1981-1983 (Box 17)
      - Student Organizations, 1978-1983
        - Activities and Programs, 1978-1981 (Box 17)
        - Funding Requests, 1979-1983 (Box 17)
      - Trotter House, 1972-1983 (Box 17)
      - University Activities Center, 1977-1980 (Box 17)
      - WCBN, 1979-1981 (Box 17)
    - 1984-1985 Annual File, 1984-1985
      - Affirmative Action, 1979-1983 (Box 17)
      - Budget Priorities Committee, 1979-1984 (Box 17)
      - Community Services, 1983-1985 (Box 17)
      - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 17)
      - Counseling ("Management of Suicidal Behavior"), 1976-1983 (Box 17)
      - Harvard Institute for Educational Management, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - 1984-1985 Annual File, 1984-1985 (cont.)
      - Michigan Student Assembly, "Fee Assessment Proposal,", 1983 (Box 18)
      - Michigan Union, 1983-1985 (Box 18)
      - Michigan Vice-Presidents, 1980-1984 (Box 18)
      - Michigan Student Services, 1980-1984 (Box 18)
      - Shapiro-Johnson Correspondence and Memos, 1983-1984 (Box 18)
      - Student Code, 1983-1984 (Box 18)
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files (17.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically. Specific files known to have been generated by a particular sub-unit have been placed under that sub- unit's name. Reports have been placed with the files of the unit that generated or collected them. When Vice President Maureen Hartford started her tenure in 1992, the name of the office changed from Vice President for Student Services to Vice President for Student Affairs. Files in this series from the office of Henry Johnson are found under the heading "Student Services, Office of". As with previous accessions, the topical files are comprised of correspondence, reports, memos, minutes and financial reports. In addition, the researcher will find program grants/proposals and student organization listings.
    A variety of topics ranging from child care to Michigan Stadium policy are covered in this series. The term See Also has been incorporated in the contents list to direct researchers to headings that contain material of a related nature. An index (page 37) has been added which contains commonly used terms and names and provides their actual contents list headings. A list of commonly used acronyms is found on page ix. When examining the files under a specific topic, the researcher should inspect "General" folders as well as folders with specific headings. Additionally, the researcher should inspect the correspondence of Henry Johnson which is located under the heading "Johnson, Henry.". The correspondence, which is in chronological order, contains information relevant to various topics found throughout the series.
    The overall function of the Office of Student Services is best documented in the "Historical Information" and "Goals and Objectives" folders. The "Minutes of the Director's Meetings" are also useful. These biweekly staff meetings were attended by Vice President Johnson and the director of each Student Service sub-unit. Topics discussed at these meetings and found in the minutes include presidential directives, unit updates, and student concerns. When examining the records of various sub-units, the researcher should always consult the contents of the "Monthly Reports to the Vice President" and any "Goals/Purpose" folders. They provide the best summaries of the focus of the individual sub-units and areas in which they concentrated their efforts.
    One of the strengths of the records in this series is documentation of the response by the university to drug use on campus during the 1970s. The Drug Education Project, funded by the U.S. Office of Education and the Office of Student Services, was created to integrate drug education and training into the daily life of the university. Four target groups were selected: staff in residence halls, counseling facilitators, students in the social sciences and administrators. After training they, in turn, educated students about the problems associated with using drugs and the resources available to assist those with drug difficulties. Some of the best documentation concerns the training of the Resident Assistants and how they were to interact with students under their jurisdiction. Another response by the university was the publication of the booklet About Drugs Again. This booklet, an updated version of All About Drugs, was published and distributed by the Drug Education Project. Considered an "abstract of factual information" about drugs, it was distributed to all students living in university owned housing. About Drugs Again was intended to educate the individual about the harmful effects of drug use and to enable the individual to discuss drugs in an informed manner. The files on this booklet provide good insight to the concerns the university had regarding the drug problem. The files on About Drugs Again can be found under the heading "Drugs". Other headings that have related information are "Alcohol," "Substance Abuse," and "Counseling Services." The latter sub-unit generated several interesting reports on substance abuse at the university.
    Another area well documented in the series is the struggle of minority students for recognition, especially African Americans. The folders within "Minority Students" document the need of Native Americans, African Americans and Chicano Americans to be represented within the university bureaucracy by a liaison/advocate. The "Afro-American Cultural Living Unit" file under "Housing" provides good documentation of the unsuccessful drive to create separate living centers on campus for African Americans and those interested in African heritage. The William Monroe Trotter House, organized in 1971, was established to serve as a center for Black student needs, both educational and social. The Trotter House provided study areas, meeting rooms for faculty and staff, formal and informal classes, orientation for high school students, and social activities. The struggle of African Americans for acceptance and recognition on campus is further documented under the headings "Office of Minority Affairs," "Discrimination," "Diversity," "Racism," and the several "Black" organizations. The establishment of "Diversity Day" (originally Martin Luther King Day) by the university in 1987 acknowledged the contributions of the many minorities on campus. The "Diversity Day" files, found under the heading "Diversity," contain listings of the many university sponsored activities for this event. The "International Center" files document such topics as enrollment, orientation, and immigration regulations pertaining to foreign students at the university.
    Project Community, a unit of Student Services, consists of student-run volunteer programs concentrated primarily in the Ann Arbor community. Recognized nationally, Project Community has two main goals: to provide individual attention to students of all ages and to stimulate new approaches and techniques in education. This program includes a mental health half-way house, a day care project, a resource center, tutorial programs for public school children, and community service programs in which undergraduate students worked with local social welfare agencies. Many of the projects sponsored by Project Community are documented in its files.
    - Academic Planning Analysis Committee (Enrollment Analysis Project), 1974 (Box 19)
    - Academic Support Services Task Force, 1982 (Box 19)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Commencement, 1984-1988 (Box 19)
    - Ad-Hoc Committee on Mandatory Student Health Insurance, 1987-1988 (Box 19)
    - Advisory Committee on Recreational, Intramural and Club Sports (ACRICS), 1973-1977 (Box 19)
    - Affirmative Action, 1985 (Box 19)
    - Aids Task Force, 1986 (Box 19)
    - Alcohol -See Also Counseling Services-Alcohol, 1983-1986; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Alumnae Council, Report to, 1978 (Box 19)
    - Ann Arbor Community Coalition
      - General (includes meeting minutes), 1971-1973 (Box 19)
      - Budget Materials, 1973 (Box 19)
      - National Drug Education Quarterly Reports, 1973; 4 folders (Box 19)
      - Proposals, 1970; 1973 (Box 19)
      - A Third-Year Proposal, 1973-1974 (Box 19)
    - Ann Arbor Sportsman Athletic Counseling, 1975 (Box 19)
    - Art Fair, 1971-1974 (Box 19)
    - Association of Black Professional Administrators, 1986-1987 (Box 19)
    - Bangladesh Relief Fund, 1972 (Box 19)
    - Black Action Movement (BAM I) (demands & resolutions)-See Also-Diversity-Black Action Movement III, 1970 (Box 19)
    - Black Alumni
      - Advisory Committee, 1980-1984 (Box 19)
      - Lists of, 1980-1984 (Box 19)
    - Black Faculty Members, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Black Leadership Council (Articles of Procedure), 1981 (Box 19)
    - Black Medical Association, 1972-1976 (Box 19)
    - Black Student Union, 1972-1973; 1987-1989 (Box 19)
    - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics-Student Appointments, 1978-1979 (Box 19)
    - Board of Student Publications, 1985 (Box 19)
    - Book Exchange, Student, 1989 (Box 19)
    - Bus Service, 1970-1971 (Box 19)
    - Calendaring Committee, 1968-1971 (Box 19)
    - Campus Ambiance, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Campus Broadcasting Network
      - General, 1988 (Box 19)
      - Board of Directors Minutes, 1983-1989; 4 folders (Box 19)
      - WCBN
        - General, 1970-1989; 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Power Increase, 1985 (Box 19)
        - Survey, 1979 (Box 19)
    - Campus Broadcasting Network (cont.)
      - WJJX (includes materials re: racial incident), 1987-1988 (Box 20)
    - Campus Compact, 1987 (Box 20)
    - Campus Information Center, 1983-1989 (Box 20)
    - Campus Safety Committee
      - General, 1986-1988 (Box 20)
      - Minutes, 1980-1989 (Box 20)
    - Career, Planning & Placement
      - General, 1977-1990; 4 folders (Box 20)
      - Budget, 1986; 1988 (Box 20)
      - CIA Protest
        - General, 1987 (Box 20)
        - Police Report, 1987; 1 folder (Box 36)
          [Student records restricted until July 01, 2072 ]
      - Goals and Objectives, 1975-1986 (Box 20)
      - Minority Program, 1978 (Box 20)
      - Non-Academic Career Counseling, 1975-1978 (Box 20)
      - Program Evaluation Committee, 1978 (Box 20)
      - Proposals, 1987 (Box 20)
      - Report
        - An Evaluative Report on the Usefulness of the System for Interactive Guidance and Information (SIGI) to University of Michigan Students, 1984 (Box 20)
      - Report to the Vice President (monthly), 1984-1987 (Box 20)
      - Unit Policy Committee (minutes), 1971-1974 (Box 20)
      - Year-End Evaluation, 1985; 1989 (Box 20)
    - Campus Disorder- Campus Disorder-Planning, 1971 (Box 20)
    - Child Care
      (See Also-Madelon Pound House)
      - General, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
        (includes 1973 child care survey)
      - Advocate, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
      - Child Care Action Center, 1972-1973; 1979; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - North Campus Task Force, 1980 (Box 20)
    - Civil Liberties Board, 1977-1988; 1986-1988 (Box 20)
    - Center for Listing University Student Events (CLUE), 1973 (Box 20)
    - College Community Program, circa 1986 (Box 20)
    - Commission on Student Governance, 1973 (Box 20)
    - Committee on
      - Access to Administrative Data, 1977 (Box 20)
      - Communication, 1977 (Box 20)
      - Diversity, 1986 (Box 20)
      - Standards and Conduct, 1965-1966 (Box 20)
      - Student Development and Experiential Education
        - General, 1984 (Box 20)
        - Report to the Vice President, 1984 (Box 20)
      - Student Relations, 1973-1980; 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Community Agent Training Program, 1972 (Box 20)
    - Community Relations, Student, 1969 (Box 20)
    - Community Services
      - General, 1973-1984 (Box 21)
      - Budget, 1971-1974 (Box 21)
      - Goals and Objectives, 1973-1988 (Box 21)
      - Monthly Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
      - Program Evaluations, 1978 (Box 21)
      - Proposals, 1973-1977 (Box 21)
    - Compensation Program Task Force, 1989 (Box 21)
    - Comprehensive Studies Program, 1988 (Box 21)
    - Constituency Advocates (minutes), 1972-1973 (Box 21)
    - Constituency Services, 1972-1973 (Box 21)
    - Council for Advancement of Standards (CAS), 1984; 1987 (Box 21)
    - Counseling Services
      - General, 1971-1989; 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Alcohol
        - General, 1971-1977 (Box 21)
        - Training Program, 1973 (Box 21)
      - Budget, 1972-1989 (Box 21)
      - Combined Drug/Sex Education Program, 1970 (Box 21)
      - Community Resources, 1970; 1978 (Box 21)
      - Coordination of Counseling Task Force (minutes), 1971-1973 (Box 21)
      - Counseling Task Force
        - General, 1976-1982 (Box 21)
        - Functional Review, 1983 (Box 21)
      - Educational Programming and Consultation Unit, 1973; 1976 (Box 21)
      - Goals, 1973-1979 (Box 21)
      - Marital/Pre-Marital Services, 1966 (Box 21)
      - Minority Programs, 1987-1988 (Box 21)
      - Minority Task Force, 1972-1973 (Box 21)
      - Peer Counseling Assertiveness Training (PCAT), 1976 (Box 21)
      - Pilot Study (Changing Patterns of Substance Abuse), 1973 (Box 21)
      - Proposal-Time-Limited Psychotherapy of Neurotic Depression, 1984 (Box 21)
      - Report to the Vice President (monthly), 1984-1987 (Box 21)
      - Reports
        - Changing Patterns of Substance Use on Campus: A Four Year Follow Up Study, circa 1974 (Box 21)
        - Freshman Difficulties in Achieving Self-Regulation: A Partial Report with Suggestions for Supportive Services, 1973 (Box 21)
        - Homosexuality and Counseling, 1972 (Box 21)
        - Report of the Committee on the Organizational Location of the Counseling Center, 1979 (Box 21)
        - Report of the University Task Force on Student Counseling, 1976 (Box 21)
        - Report to Campus Task Force on Management of Suicidal Behavior, 1982 (Box 21)
        - Substance Use Patterns in the First Year Class at the University of Michigan in 1974, 1976 (Box 21)
        - The Drug Education Project at the University of Michigan: Overview of Organization, Accomplishments, and Recommendations, 1975 (Box 21)
        - Training Needs and Roles of Resident Advisors: A Preliminary Report, 1975 (Box 21)
        - Using Social Indicators of the Quality of Life For Improving the College Experience, 1976 (Box 21)
      - Self Regulation Study, 1968-1970 (Box 21)
      - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1971-1973; 3 folders (Box 21)
      - Student Need Assessment Survey, 1974 (Box 21)
      - Task Force on Problem Pregnancy, 1970-1972 (Box 21)
      - Training Task Force, 1974 (Box 21)
      - Unit Committee (minutes), 1971-1972 (Box 21)
    - Crema, Annette (Program Development Consultant), 1988-1989 (Box 21)
    - Creole Fundacion, 1971-1972 (Box 21)
    - Death/Injury/Trauma Policy, 1986 (Box 21)
    - Detroit Public Schools, 1986 (Box 21)
    - Diag
      - General, 1973-1988 (Box 21)
      - Guidelines for Usage, 1969-1988 (Box 21)
    - Disabled Student Services (Box 22)
      (See Also-Student Services, Office Of)
      - General, 1971-1987 (Box 22)
      - Breakthrough Scholarship Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 22)
      - Concerns, 1981-1989 (Box 22)
      - Emergency Evacuation, 1983-1985 (Box 22)
      - Grievances, 1988 (Box 36)
        [Student records restricted until July 01, 2073 ]
      - Parking Permits, 1981; 1989 (Box 22)
      - Project Write Proposal, 1985 (Box 22)
      - Report
        - Handicapped Student Program, 1968-1969 (Box 22)
      - Section 504 Self-Evaluation Questionnaires, 1978 (Box 22)
        (completed by individual units, re: handicapped accommodations)
      - Transportation, 1980-1989 (Box 22)
    - Discrimination
      (See Also-Racism)
      - General, 1988 (Box 22)
      - Grievances, 1988-1989 (Box 36)
        [Student records restricted until July 01, 2074 ]
      - Harassment Statistics, 1988-1989 (Box 22)
      - Policies and Procedures, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
      - Sexual Orientation, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
    - Diversity
      (See Also-Minority Students, Student Services, Office of)
      - General, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
      - Black Action Movement (BAM) III (list of demands), 1987 (Box 22)
      - Diversity Day, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
        (See Also-Martin Luther King Day)
      - Orientation Programming, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
      - Retreat, 1987 (Box 22)
      - Task Force, 1986 (Box 22)
    - Drug Education Project
      - General, 1971-1973 (Box 22)
        (includes explanation of the project and 1972 annual report)
      - Films, 1973 (Box 22)
      - Management by Objectives, 1973 (Box 22)
      - Proposals, 1970-1973 (Box 22)
      - Report
        - Student Attitudes Toward Drug Education Programs at the University of Michigan, 1969 (Box 22)
      - Research Plan
        - General, 1973 (Box 22)
        - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 22)
      - Resident Assistant (R.A.) Training Program
        - General, 1971-1973; 3 folders (Box 22)
        - Evaluation Results, 1971-1972; 1974; 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Drug Emergency Center and Adjunct House (Drug Help, Inc)
      - General, 1969-1972
        (includes minutes of ad hoc committee on adjunct centers)
        - Quaalude Information, 1973 (Box 22)
    - Drugs
      - General, 1967-1971 (Box 22)
      - About Drugs Again
        - Copyright Permission, 1972-1974 (Box 22)
        - Evaluation Originals, (undated) (Box 22)
        - Distribution and Reprinting, 1969-1973 (Box 22)
        - Revision Items, 1974-1975 (Box 22)
      - American Personnel and Guidance Association Presentation, 1975 (Box 23)
      - Bibliographies, undated (Box 23)
      - Crisis Information, undated (Box 23)
      - Drug Courses, 1971; 1973 (Box 23)
      - Drug Education
        - Survey of Student Attitudes, 1968 (Box 23)
        - Training Program, 1970-1976 (Box 23)
      - Information Surveys, 1968-1969 (Box 23)
      - Report
        - Drug Observations: Program for Experiments (DOPE), 1973 (Box 23)
      - Washtenaw County Problem Solver Drug Manual, 1974 (Box 23)
      - Working Committee on Drugs
        - Materials Sub-Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 23)
        - Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 23)
        - Program Sub-Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 23)
        - Survey Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 23)
    - Eclipse Jazz, 1983; 1990 (Box 23)
    - Ecumenical Campus Center, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Engineering Council (re: student fee increase), 1988 (Box 23)
    - English Language Institute
      - General, 1972-1974 (Box 23)
      - Evaluation, Student, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Japanese Teachers of English
        - General, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
        - Course Evaluation, 1982 (Box 23)
    - Ethics & Religion, Office of
      - General, 1972-1978; 1980-1989; 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Budget, 1971-1974 (Box 23)
      - Concerns, 1978 (Box 23)
      - Goals and Purpose, 1969-1978; 1989 (Box 23)
      - Proposals, 1972-1973 (Box 23)
    - Foreign Faculty/Staff Coordinator, 1971-1974 (Box 23)
    - Foreign Students
      (-See Also-International Center)
      - Financial Aid, 1971-1973 (Box 23)
      - Foreign Student Board, 1971-1972 (Box 23)
      - Health Insurance, 1973-1974; 1978; 1984 (Box 23)
    - Freshman Convocation, 1984; 1986-1988 (Box 23)
    - Fulbright Grant, 1978; 1988 (Box 23)
    - Future Worlds (study of futuristics), 1974 (Box 23)
    - Greeks
      - General, 1970-1988; 4 folders (Box 23)
      - Activities Review Panel, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Alkon Case, 1986 (Box 36)
        [Student records restricted until July 01, 2071 ]
      - Alumni-Interfraternity Council, 1989 (Box 23)
      - Black Greek Task Force, 1986 (Box 23)
      - Fraternities
        - Alpha Delta Phi (re: cat incident), 1979-1980 (Box 23)
        - Alpha Phi Alpha, 1977 (Box 23)
        - Alpha Phi Omega (re: blood bank), 1972 (Box 23)
        - Delta Tau Delta, 1985-1987 (Box 23)
        - Phi Kappa Tau, 1984 (Box 23)
        - Pi Kappa Phi, 1983 (Box 23)
        - Sigma Chi, 1986-1987 (Box 23)
      - Fraternity/Sorority Listings, 1967-1989 (scattered dates) (Box 23)
      - Fraternity Coordinating Council, 1978; 1980 (Box 23)
      - Greek Task Force
        - General, 1986 (Box 23)
        - Report, 1986 (Box 23)
        - Concerns, 1987-1989 (Box 23)
      - Hazing
        - General, 1981-1986 (Box 23)
        - Concerns, 1987-1989 (Box 23)
      - Historical Information, 1986 (Box 24)
      - Sororities
        - General, 1981-1988 (Box 24)
        - Alpha Kappa Alpha, 1983-1989 (Box 24)
        - Collegiate Sorosis, 1985 (Box 24)
        - Sigma Kappa, 1987 (Box 24)
    - Grievance Procedures, Student, 1976-1977 (Box 24)
    - Housing
      - General, 1971-1989; 6 folders (Box 24)
      - Afro-American Cultural Living Units, 1972 (Box 24)
      - Alcohol Education, 1985-1986 (Box 24)
      - Building Directors Meetings, 1971-1972 (Box 24)
      - Concerns, 1978-1989 (Box 24)
      - Council, 1972 (Box 24)
      - Discrimination and Harassment, 1989 (Box 24)
      - Educational Programs, 1988 (Box 24)
      - Family Housing
        - General, 1978-1979 (Box 24)
        - Monthly Reports, 1985-1989 (Box 24)
      - Goals, Purpose & History, 1978 (Box 24)
      - Grievances
        - 1978-1989, 1 folder (Box 24)
        - 1978-1989, 1 folder (Box 36)
      - Guidelines and Regulations, 1964-1968 (Box 24)
      - Honors Housing, 1973 (Box 24)
      - Hughes, Robert (Housing Director), 1978 (Box 24)
      - Investigative Case Reports, 1976-1989; 2 folders (Box 36)
      - Language Houses, 1972-1973 (Box 24)
      - Markley Hall Incident, 1989 (Box 36)
      - Minority Occupancy, 1975-1985 (Box 24)
      - Monthly Reports to the Vice President, 1984-1988; 4 folders (Box 24)
      - North Campus Community Center, 1967-1988 (Box 24)
      - Northwood V Task Force (minutes), 1977 (Box 24)